<class
    name = "mlm_proto"
    title = "The Malamute Protocol"
    script = "zproto_codec_c"
    package_dir = "../include"
    project_header = "mlm_classes.h"
    signature = "8"
    export_macro = "MLM_EXPORT"
    >
    This is a codec for the Malamute Protocol (RFC tbd)
    <include filename = "license.xml" />

    <grammar>
    Malamute = open ( traffic / heartbeat ) close

    open = C:CONNECTION-OPEN ( S:OK / S:ERROR )

    traffic = stream-traffic / mailbox-traffic / service-traffic / credit

    stream-traffic = C:STREAM-WRITE ( S:OK / S:ERROR )
                   / C:STREAM-READ
                   / C:STREAM-CANCEL
                   / C:STREAM-PUBLISH
                   / S:STREAM-DELIVER
    
    mailbox-traffic = C:MAILBOX-SEND ( S:OK [ S:CONFIRM ] / S:ERROR )
                    / S:MAILBOX-DELIVER [ C:CONFIRM ]
    
    service-traffic = C:SERVICE-SEND ( S:OK [ S:CONFIRM ] / S:ERROR )
                    / C:SERVICE-OFFER 
                    / S:SERVICE-DELIVER [ C:CONFIRM ]

    credit = C:CREDIT
    
    heartbeat = C:CONNECTION-PING ( S:CONNECTION-PONG / S:ERROR )

    close = C:CONNECTION-CLOSE ( S:OK / S:ERROR )
    </grammar>

    <!-- Opening and closing the connection -->
    <message name = "CONNECTION OPEN">
        Client opens a connection to the server. Client can ask for a mailbox
        by specifying an address. If mailbox does not exist, server creates it.
        Server replies with OK or ERROR.
        <field name = "protocol" type = "string" value = "MALAMUTE">Constant "MALAMUTE"</field>
        <field name = "version" type = "number" size = "2" value = "1">Protocol version 1</field>
        <field name = "address" type = "string">Client address</field>
    </message>
    
    <message name = "CONNECTION PING">
        Client pings the server. Server replies with CONNECTION-PONG, or
        ERROR with status COMMAND-INVALID if the client is not recognized
        (e.g. after a server restart or network recovery).
    </message>

    <message name = "CONNECTION PONG">
        Server replies to a client connection ping.
    </message>
    
    <message name = "CONNECTION CLOSE">
        Client closes the connection. This is polite though not mandatory.
        Server will reply with OK or ERROR.
    </message>

    <!-- Stream operations -->
    <message name = "STREAM WRITE">
        Client declares intention to write to a stream. If stream does not
        exist, server creates it. A client can write to a single stream at
        once. Server replies with OK or ERROR. 
        <field name = "stream" type = "string">Name of stream</field>
    </message>
    
    <message name = "STREAM READ">
        Client opens a stream for reading, specifying a pattern to match
        message subjects. An empty pattern matches everything. If the stream
        does not exist, the server creates it. A client can read from many
        streams at once. It can also read from the same stream many times,
        with different patterns. Server replies with OK or ERROR.
        <field name = "stream" type = "string">Name of stream</field>
        <field name = "pattern" type = "string">Match message subjects</field>
    </message>

    <message name = "STREAM SEND">
        Client publishes a message to the current stream. A stream message
        has a subject, and a content of zero or more frames. Server does not
        reply to this message. The subject is used to match messages to
        readers. A reader will receive a given message at most once.
        <field name = "subject" type = "string">Message subject</field>
        <field name = "content" type = "msg">Message body frames</field>
    </message>

    <message name = "STREAM DELIVER">
        Server delivers a stream message to a client. The delivered message
        has the address of the original sending client, so clients can send
        messages back to the original sender's mailbox if they need to.
        <field name = "address" type = "string">Name of stream</field>
        <field name = "sender" type = "string">Sending client address</field>
        <field name = "subject" type = "string">Message subject</field>
        <field name = "content" type = "msg">Message body frames</field>
    </message>
    
    <!-- Mailbox operations -->
    <message name = "MAILBOX SEND">
        Client sends a message to a specified mailbox. Client does not open the
        mailbox before sending a message to it. Server replies with OK when it
        accepts the message, or ERROR if that failed. If the tracker is not
        empty, the sender can expect a CONFIRM at some later stage, for this
        message. Confirmations are asynchronous. If the message cannot be
        delivered within the specified timeout (zero means infinite), the server
        discards it and returns a CONFIRM with a TIMEOUT-EXPIRED status.
        <field name = "address" type = "string">Mailbox address</field>
        <field name = "subject" type = "string">Message subject</field>
        <field name = "tracker" type = "string">Message tracker</field>
        <field name = "timeout" type = "number" size = "4">Timeout, msecs, or zero</field>
        <field name = "content" type = "msg">Message body frames</field>
    </message>

    <message name = "MAILBOX DELIVER">
        Server delivers a mailbox message to client. Note that client does not 
        open its own mailbox for reading; this is implied in CONNECTION-OPEN.
        If tracker is not empty, client must respond with CONFIRM when it
        formally accepts delivery of the message, or if the server delivers
        the same message a second time.
        <field name = "sender" type = "string">Sending client address</field>
        <field name = "address" type = "string">Mailbox address</field>
        <field name = "subject" type = "string">Message subject</field>
        <field name = "tracker" type = "string">Message tracker</field>
        <field name = "content" type = "msg">Message body frames</field>
    </message>

    <!-- Service queue operations -->
    <message name = "SERVICE SEND">
        Client sends a service request to a service queue. Server replies with
        OK when queued, or ERROR if that failed. If the tracker is not
        empty, the client can expect a CONFIRM at some later time.
        Confirmations are asynchronous. If the message cannot be delivered
        within the specified timeout (zero means infinite), the server
        discards it and returns CONFIRM with a TIMEOUT-EXPIRED status.
        <field name = "address" type = "string">Service address</field>
        <field name = "subject" type = "string">Message subject</field>
        <field name = "tracker" type = "string">Message tracker</field>
        <field name = "timeout" type = "number" size = "4">Timeout, msecs, or zero</field>
        <field name = "content" type = "msg">Message body frames</field>
    </message>

    <message name = "SERVICE OFFER">
        Worker client offers a named service, specifying a pattern to match
        message subjects. An empty pattern matches anything. A worker can offer
        many different services at once. Server replies with OK or ERROR.
        <field name = "address" type = "string">Service address</field>
        <field name = "pattern" type = "string">Match message subjects</field>
    </message>

    <message name = "SERVICE DELIVER">
        Server delivers a service request to a worker client. If tracker
        is not empty, worker must respond with CONFIRM when it accepts delivery
        of the message. The worker sends replies to the request to the requesting
        client's mailbox.
        <field name = "sender" type = "string">Sending client address</field>
        <field name = "address" type = "string">Service address</field>
        <field name = "subject" type = "string">Message subject</field>
        <field name = "tracker" type = "string">Message tracker</field>
        <field name = "content" type = "msg">Message body frames</field>
    </message>
    
    <!-- These messages are used in all classes -->
    <message name = "OK">
        Server replies with success status. Actual status code provides more
        information. An OK always has a 2xx status code.
        <field name = "status" type = "status" />
    </message>

    <message name = "ERROR">
        Server replies with failure status. Actual status code provides more
        information. An ERROR always has a 3xx, 4xx, or 5xx status code.
        <field name = "status" type = "status" />
    </message>

    <message name = "CREDIT">
        Client sends credit to allow delivery of messages. Until the client
        sends credit, the server will not deliver messages. The client can send
        further credit at any time. Credit is measured in number of messages.
        Server does not reply to this message. Note that credit applies to all
        stream, mailbox, and service deliveries.
        <field name = "amount" type = "number" size = "2">Number of messages</field>
    </message>

    <message name = "CONFIRM">
        Client confirms reception of a message, or server forwards this
        confirmation to original sender. If status code is 300 or higher, this
        indicates that the message could not be delivered.
        <field name = "tracker" type = "string">Message tracker</field>
        <field name = "status" type = "status" />
    </message>

<!-- version protocol 2 -->
    <message name = "STREAM CANCEL">
        Cancels and removes all subscriptions to a stream . 
        Server replies with OK or ERROR.
        <field name = "stream" type = "string">Name of stream</field>
    </message>

    <type name = "status">
        <field name = "code" type = "number" size = "2">3-digit status code</field>
        <field name = "reason" type = "string">Printable explanation</field>
    </type>

    <!-- Success codes -->
    <define name = "SUCCESS" value = "200" />

    <!-- Temporary errors -->
    <define name = "FAILED" value = "300" />

    <!-- System errors -->
    <define name = "COMMAND INVALID" value = "500" />
    <define name = "NOT IMPLEMENTED" value = "501" />
    <define name = "INTERNAL ERROR" value = "502" />
</class>
